Guide to the Marvin and Theresa (Terry) Miller Papers WAG.165
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Marvin J. Miller and Theresa (Terry) Miller Papers
Bulk, 1966-1990
1919-2009
WAG.165
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
13.75 linear feet in 11 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, and 2 flat boxes
Marvin Julian Miller (1917-2012) was the executive director of the Major League Baseball Players Association from 1966-1983, and was instrumental in its development into a powerful labor union that transformed the economics and labor relations of baseball, which led ultimately to profound changes in the nature of U.S. professional sports and their place in society. After his retirement in 1983, he continued to be active as a consultant to the Players Association and a frequent commentator on labor relations in sports, labor and economic history and current affairs. The collection includes correspondence, minutes, reports, legal documents, research and historical materials, photographs, articles, clippings and videocassettes that document Miller's career, principally with the MLBPA, and to a lesser extent, his earlier work for the United Steelworkers of America and in several labor-related U.S. government positions. The papers of his wife, psychologist Theresa (Terry) Miller (1919-), are also part of the collection.
Miller, Marvin, 1917-2012
Miller, Theresa, 1919-
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated by Marvin and Theresa Miller in several batches between July 2001 and March 2003. An additional donation, consisting mostly of Theresa Miller's papers, was made in 2012 by their daughter, Susan Miller. A donation of 61 videocassettes was added by Susan Miller on April 16, 2013. The accession number associated with this donation is 2013.008.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Marvin Julian Miller was born in New York City on April 14, 1917 and raised in Brooklyn. His father, Alexander Miller, was a salesman in the garment district and a devoted Giants fan; his mother, Gertrude Wald Miller, was an elementary-school teacher. Miller studied first at Miami University of Ohio and then at New York University, where he received a B.S. degree in economics in 1938. In the same year he married Theresa Morgenstern; they had two children, Peter, born in 1945, and Susan, born in 1949. Theresa Miller went on to earn a Ph.D. in psychology in 1961 and, after working in clinical and experimental psychology, retired as an Associate Professor at the City University of New York.
After graduation from NYU, Marvin Miller worked briefly for the New York City Welfare Department and went on to positions as a staff economist at the War Production Board and an economist and disputes hearing officer for the War Labor Board. In the post-war period he worked for the United States Department of Labor's Conciliation Service. After brief stints with the International Association of Machinists and the United Auto Workers, he was hired in 1950 as a research economist for the United Steelworkers of America. There Miller worked with general counsel Arthur Goldberg to develop the Steelworkers' innovative and successful post-war collective bargaining strategy. When Goldberg left to become President John F. Kennedy's Secretary of Labor, Miller became the union's chief economist and negotiator, and assistant to Steelworkers president David J. McDonald.
In December 1965 former Philadelphia Phillies pitcher Robin Roberts, representing the Major League Baseball Players Association, contacted Marvin Miller about the newly-envisioned position of full-time Executive Director of the MLBPA. After a long interview process and discussions with all the major league teams, against the back-drop of the Sandy Koufax-Don Drysdale holdout in the spring of 1966, Miller was elected to the new post by an overwhelming majority of players, managers, coaches and trainers. He was joining an organization that lacked staff, adequate office space, a war chest and the full confidence of its constituency. Visionary player-advocates like Roberts and Phillies delegate Jim Bunning were the exception in a culture bound by paternalism, sentimentality and deep divisions based on age, ethnicity, race and status. The owners, too, were often divided and short-sighted, relying too much on a cozy relationship with the media and legal establishments.
When Miller began as Executive Director, major league baseball was at a crossroads. Television revenue had increased dramatically but the owners, armed with a reserve rules system that bound every professional baseball player for his entire career to the franchise that had "drafted" and signed him (unless sold to another organization), were keeping salaries, pensions and other benefits at pre-television-era levels. In 1966 the average salary of a major league player was $19,000 a year; the minimum annual salary of $6,000 was only $1,000 above the 1947 minimum.
Miller applied his expertise as a labor economist and negotiator, as well as his human relations and organizing skills, to his new job, and scored some significant bargaining victories. His first Basic Agreement, signed in 1968, doubled pension levels, raised salary minimums and addressed a variety of player complaints about working conditions. These gains and new licensing arrangements which directly benefited players, plus Miller's frequent tours of training camps and open-door policy at his New York office, soon overcame player resistance - even in the face of the owners' persistent efforts to label him a "labor boss" and a communist.
In 1969 Curt Flood, an African-American and the St. Louis Cardinals' star center fielder, was abruptly notified that he had been traded to the Philadelphia Phillies, a team with a reputation for poor race relations. He decided to wage a legal battle against being uprooted and traded as merchandise against his will. After warning Flood of the tough struggle ahead and possible damage to his career prospects, the MLBPA Executive Board, on Miller's recommendation, agreed to back the effort and cover Flood's legal and travel expenses. Miller arranged for Flood to be represented by Arthur Goldberg. After a series of appeals, the case, technically a challenge to baseball's longstanding exemption from the anti-trust laws, reached the U.S. Supreme Court. In June 1972 the Court ruled, in a 5 to 3 decision, in favor of the owners. Once again, professional baseball's uniquely paternalistic system of labor relations was upheld.
In 1972 a hard-line majority of team owners, together with Baseball Commissioner Bowie Kuhn, were determined to reverse the union's recent progress and hold the line on pensions, despite the steady growth of television revenue. The blatant anti-union motivation was obvious, since Miller had proposed a formula whereby pension increases could be achieved without additional financing from the owners.
Despite strenuous efforts by Miller to achieve a negotiated settlement the owners refused to budge, and the players went on strike on April 1, 1972. A settlement was reached on April 13th, on terms encompassing those proposed by the players' negotiating committee before the strike began. A total of eighty-six games had been cancelled in what was the first successful strike in the history of professional sports. With this demonstration of solidarity the balance of power between players and owners had shifted significantly, laying the groundwork for more changes to come.
In 1975 pitchers Andy Messersmith of the Los Angeles Dodgers and Dave McNally of the Montreal Expos, whose 1974 contracts had been renewed without their signatures or consent, filed grievances against the unilateral renewal procedure. In effect, it was a challenge to the Reserve Clause, with the owners, as usual refusing to negotiate. Peter Seitz's arbitration decision in the case, delivered on December 23, 1975, upheld the players. The 1976 Basic Agreement included a guarantee of "the right of players under their present contracts to become free agents" after serving six years with the team that first signed them. Miller was immediately hailed as baseball's "Great Emancipator."
The owners regrouped and mounted another offensive in 1981 - demanding compensation for the loss of free agents. On the advice of Miller, Association general counsel Donald Fehr, former counsel Richard Moss, and their own Negotiating Committee, the players struck on May 29th. Player solidarity held, despite a barrage of press criticism and furious protests from fans. A settlement was achieved, again on terms originally proposed by the Association, and players returned to the field on August 1st.
When Marvin Miller retired in 1983 he was widely considered to be the most effective labor leader of his generation. He continues to be active as a consultant to the Players Association and a frequent commentator on labor relations in sports, labor and economic history and current affairs. In 1991 he published a volume of memoirs, A Whole Different Ball Game: The Sport and Business of Baseball(New York: Birch Lane Press), with a preface by Studs Terkel and an introduction by Bill James. A paperback edition, published by Simon and Schuster in the same year, bore a revised subtitle, perhaps more in keeping with the Miller philosophy: The Inside Story of Baseball's New Deal. Miller has been the recipient of many honors and awards. Sport Magazine in 1982 called him "one of the five most powerful men in sports," and ESPN-TV in 1999 deemed him fourth among the ten "most influential in all sports in the twentieth century."
Marvin Miller died in 2012 at the age of 95.
Sources:
Angell, Roger. Late Innings: A Baseball Companion. New York, Simon and Schuster, 1982. Chapter on 1981 strike.
Belth, Alex. Stepping Up: The Story of Curt Flood and His Fight for Baseball Players’ Rights. New York: Persea Books
Bevis, Charles W. "A Home Run by Any Measure: The Baseball Players' Pension Plan," Baseball Research Journal, 21 (1992).
Burk, Robert F. Much More than a Game: Owners, Players and American Baseball since 1921. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 2001.
Dworkin, James B. Owners versus Players: Baseball and Collective Bargaining. Boston: Auburn House, 1981.
Flood, Curt and Richard Carter. The Way It Is. New York, Trident Press, 1971.
Helyar, John. Lords of the Realm: The Real History of Baseball. New York: Villard Books, 1994.
Koppett, Leonard. The New Thinking Fan's Guide to Baseball. New York: Simon and Shuster, 1991. Chapter 18, "The Players Association."
Korr, Charles P. "Marvin Miller and the New Unionism in Baseball," in The Business of Professional Sports, ed. Paul D. Staudohar and James A. Mangan. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1991.
Kuhn, Bowie. Hardball: The Education of a Baseball Commissioner. New York: Times Books, 1987.
Lowenfish, Lee. The Imperfect Diamond: A History of Baseball's Labor Wars rev. ed., New York: Da Capo, 1991.
Miller, Marvin. A Whole Different Ball Game: The Sport and Business of Baseball. New York: Birch Lane Press, 1991.
Snyder, Brad. A Well-Paid Slave: Curt Flood's Fight for Free Agency in Professional Sports. New York: Viking, 2006.
Yasser, Ray. Sports Law: Cases and Materials. Lanham, MD: University Presses of America, 1985. Section on the Messersmith-McNally decision.
Scope and Content Note
The Marvin Miller Papers document Miller's nearly two decades of leadership in the Major League Baseball Players Association (MLBPA). The collection is largely comprised of photocopied articles from both local and national newspapers and magazines on the strikes of 1972 and 1981, litigation on the Reserve Clause, and other events during Miller's management of the MLBPA. The collection also consists of correspondence, legal documents, reports, newsletters, research, oral histories, videotapes, and photographs which trace the history of the MLBPA and Miller's work with the union. Most materials date from Miller’s term as Executive Director from the mid-1960s to the early 1980s, but some materials on the history of baseball and other sports and Miller’s legacy or work as a consultant predate or postdate this period.
To a lesser extent, the collection includes reports, newsletters, clippings, and photographs related to Miller's involvement with the United Steelworkers of America, as well as his early jobs with the War Labor Board (Pennsylvania Region) and the National Wage Stabilization Board. There is also a small amount of material on the personal and professional activities of Miller's wife, Theresa.
Arrangement
Folders in series I, II, and V are arranged alphabetically and in series III and IV are arranged chronologically.
The collection is comprised of five series:
I. Early Career and United Steelworkers of America, 1944-1966
II. Major League Baseball Players Association, 1949-2002
III. Clippings Files, 1966-2002
IV. Videotapes (VHS), 1987-2002
V. Theresa (Terry) Miller Papers, 1919-1994
Flood, Curt, 1938-1997; Major League Baseball Players Association.; Miller, Marvin, 1917-2012; Miller, Theresa, 1919-; Seitz, Peter.; Topps Chewing Gum, Inc.; United Steelworkers of America.; Veeck, Bill.; Baseball cards.; Baseball players |x Labor unions.; Baseball |x History.; Clippings (information artifacts); Collective bargaining |x Baseball.; Correspondence.; Iron and steel workers |x Labor unions; Labor unions |x Baseball players |z United States |x History-20th century.; Labor unions |z United States; Legal documents.; Minutes.; New York (N.Y.); Strikes and lockouts |x Baseball |z United States.; Transcripts.; Videocassettes.
- Series I: Early Career and United Steelworkers of America, 1944-1966
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I. Early Career and United Steelworkers of America, 1944-1966, arranged alphabetically by topic. Included are a few case reports relating to Marvin Miller's work at the War Labor Board (Pennsylvania Region) and the National Wage Stabilization Board, as well as reports, newsletters, leaflets, proceedings and clippings relating to negotiations, committee work, benefits agreements and other work undertaken by Miller as research economist and assistant to the president of the United Steelworkers of America.
  - Abel Election, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alan Wood Steel Co., 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Kheel, Theodore W.: "How to Arbitrate a Labor Dispute", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - National Labor-Management Panel, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - National Wage Stabilization Board: Third Region, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Steel Strike, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Steelworkers: Convention Proceedings, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Steelworkers: General, 1951-1966, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Steelworkers: Human Relations Committee, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Steelworkers: Kaiser-Steel Long Range Committee Meeting Photographs, January 13, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Steelworkers: Kaiser-Steel Union Sharing Plan, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Steelworkers: Photographs (same event), 1962 (Box 12, Folder 10-12)
  - Steelworkers: Photographs (same event), 1963 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Steelworkers: Photographs, 1947, 1963-1966, undated (Box 12, Folder 14-17)
  - Steelworkers: Revenue Sharing Plan, undated, 1959-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Steelworkers: Savings and Vacation Plan, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Steelworkers vs. American Manufacturing Co., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - War Labor Board: Regional, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II: Major League Baseball Players Association, 1949-2005
  Series II. Major League Baseball Players Association, 1949-2002, arranged alphabetically by topic. These files include correspondence, minutes, reports, legal documents, research and historical materials, articles and clippings. They cover all aspects of Marvin Miller's work at the MLBPA, from his recruitment as Executive Director in 1965-66 to his role as a consultant after his retirement from that position in 1983. There are extensive files on each round of contract negotiations during Miller's tenure and on the strikes of 1972 and 1981. Several groups of files, notably those covering the Baltimore Orioles vs. MLBPA and Topps cases, relate to the history of radio/television and product licensing. Another group of files documents the Curt Flood case (1969-1972) and the Reserve Clause and free agency in general. Background or reference files are devoted to Marvin Miller's life, writings and public testimony, to individual players, owners and Commissioners, and to baseball history, sports journalists, and other sports unions.
  - Agents, 1966, 1977-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Agents Meetings, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Agreements, 1976, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Agreements, 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Allen, Ricard, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - AFL-CIO: Sports Unions, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Angelos, Peter, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Antitrust Hearings, 1981-1997 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Arbitration, 1974-1984 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Arbitration Cases, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Arbitration Decisions, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Arbitration Decisions, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ballinger, Lee, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Baltimore Orioles vs. MLBPA / Rogers et al. vs. Kuhn et al. (Television Litigation), Part I, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Baltimore Orioles vs. MLBPA / Rogers et al. vs. Kuhn et al. (Television Litigation), Part II, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Baltimore Orioles vs. MLBPA / Rogers et al. vs. Kuhn et al.: Motions and Affidavits, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Baseball Hall of Fame, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Baseball History: Articles, etc., 1949, 1976-1999 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Baseball History: Negotiations, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Baseball Humor, undated, 1968-1981, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Baseball Law: Evers and Fullerton, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Baseball Study Committee: Stephen Fehr Salary Study; Moss Remarks, etc., 1992 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Baseball's Money Madness" (Newsweek), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Benefit Plan, undated, 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Benefit Plan, undated, 1962-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Benefit Plan, 1971-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Benefit Plan, 1990, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Benefit Plan: Exhibits, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Benefit Plan: NLRB Exhibits, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 6A-8)
  - Benefit Plan: Negotiations, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Blue, Vida, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bonus Clauses, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Boston Red Sox: Ownership Dispute, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Boyer, Clete, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bouton, Jim, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Burke, Michael, Outrageous Good Fortune (excerpt), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Busch, August Jr., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Cannon, Robert C., 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Chicago White Sox, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Coaches and Trainers, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Collective Bargaining in Baseball: General, undated, 1956-1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Collusion Cases, 1986-1992 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Commissioners: General, 1967-1968, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Contract Depreciation, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, undated, 1966-2002 (Box 2, Folder 24-46)
  - Coscarart vs. MLBPA: Miller Testimony, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Discrimination in Baseball, 1966, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Draft System, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Drug Testing, 1985-1997 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Drugs: General, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Durocher, Leo, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Expansion, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Fans against Strike Talk (FAST), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Fehr, Donald, 1985, 1989, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Finances, undated, 1966-1988 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Finley, Charley, undated, 1967-1976 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Flood, Curt: Briefings, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Flood, Curt: Briefings, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Flood, Curt: Clippings, 1969-1986 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Free Agency, 1970-1981, 1982-1988 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Gaherin, John, 1967-1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Garagiola, Joseph, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Grebey, C. Raymond, 1980-1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Grievances, 1968-1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Hodges, Gil, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Horlen, Joe, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - House Select Committee on Professional Sports, undated, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Hoyt, La Marr: Arbitration Case, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Hunter, Jim "Catfish", 1974-1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Injuries, undated, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Japan, undated, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Jenkins, Ferguson: Arbitration (80-25), 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Johnson, Alex, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Joint Committee: MLBPA and Player Relations Committee, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Jones, Cleon, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - King and Kennedy Assassinations, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Koppett, Leonard: "The Baseball Revolution is Here!" (Sport), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Korr, Charles P., "What's Wrong with Being a Professional?", 1985 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Kuhn, Bowie, undated, 1969-1991 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
  - Leavy, Jane: Clippings, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Lee, Bill, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Length of Season, undated, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Licensing: General, 1966-1980 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Licensing: TV-Radio, 1954-1982 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - List of Players, undated, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Lowenfish, Lee, 1978, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - MacPhail Report: Excerpt, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - MLBPA: Executive Board, undated, 1974-1982 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - MLBPA: Executive Board Minutes, 1977-1982 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - MLBPA: Executive Director Search, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - MLBPA: Executive Subcommittee, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - MLBPA: Finances, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - MLBPA: General, 1967-1985 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - MLBPA: List of Representatives and Committees, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - MLBPA Newsletter, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Major League Player Relations Committee, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Major League Player Relations Committee vs. MLBPA (86-12), 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - McLain, Denny, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Messersmith/McNally Case, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Miller: Appointment as Executive Director, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Miller: Baseballs and Baseballs Cards (Signed), 1991, 2005 (Box 13)
  - Miller: Bibiliography, List of Articles, 1966-1981 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Miller Cartoons, undated, 1968-1977, 1980-1981, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Miller Clippings (Graphic), 1950s-1980s (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Miller: Contracts, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Miller: General (Clippings), undated, 1966-1999 (Box 3, Folder 50-54)
  - Miller: General, 2000-2005 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Miller: Photographs, Baseball Hall of Fame, undated, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Miller: Photographs, Book Copies, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Miller: Photographs, General, 1973, 1982, 1987, 1996, 2000 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Miller: Photographs, Portraits, 1980, undated (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
  - Miller: Photographs from Tamiment Event, May 21, 2003 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Minor Leagues, 1974-1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Moffett, Kenneth E., 1982-1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Moffett, Kenneth E.: Court Case, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Moss, Richard, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Murphy, Robert: Interview Transcript, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - National Baseball Network, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - National Basketball Association, 1967-1987 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - National Football League, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - National Football League (Clippings), undated, 1967-1994 (Box 4, Folder 10-13)